All right. Good morning.
I think we're on our live stream straight away, so we've got
Bring It Up on the Public Finance Prohibition on Providing Public Funds to
gangs Amendment Bill, and we've got the Maori Women's Welfare League presenting to
us. So Hope is going to be joining us online.
Morena.
Can you see me?
We can, Hope. Yes. Great to have you, and we can hear you as well.
We've got you down for 10 minutes. We've read your written submission, but
feel free to leave some time at the end for questions as well.
Okay. I won't really need 10 minutes, but thank you.
Do I just start?
Yep. Fire away.
Cool. Okay, thank you. Yeah, I think I'm your first person
this morning.
I just really wanted to reiterate what I've said in
our written submission about many
members of our organization have connections to people in
gangs.
And I just want to highlight to you the concern
around
the potential for the removal of access to funding for
programs around rehabilitation Whatever that is.
I've sat in Waitangi Tribunal hearings and heard
from organizations who are unable to get funding
because of their associations with gangs by
whakapapa.
And I just want to point out to you that one of the
concerns is
the words, so
Section 73A (1) ,
about the Crown must not pay money
indirectly.
So this is where the concern about
funding organizations who have got really good
programs
for, it might be
for people in gangs who
often have a history of trauma.
And
I want to also draw your attention to
the Gangs Act
because the definition includes an
association with a gang.
If people have served their crime and are out of
prison,
it just feels like they're never going to actually leave that history, that they're
never
what they've in the pa- That's really all I wanted today, because I did in my
written submission.
Great.
But I wanted to just raise to you the concerns that I have
around the wording, both in the bill that's been proposed,
as well as the connection to the Gangs Act.
So you're leaving it up to the public servants to try and
differentiate who they give their funding to and not give their funding to.
Great. Thank you, Hope. We've got a question from Dr Lawrence Sunam.
Okay.
Kia ora. Thank you, Chair. Thank you so much, Hope.
Just looking at your submission where you talk about
that, "We agree that public money should not be used to fund organized crime."
Can I just check with you then, have you given any
thoughts on what an alternative could potentially look like?
What would be your sort of ideal scenario?
Well, I think you'll know more than I do who's
actually been funded to provide programs and who's
having success with programs for things like
pastoral or trauma-led
rehabilitative and healing programs.
So I think there should be a deliberate
strategy for that investment
rather than saying the government's not going
to fund anything associated with the gangs.
There has to be something available.
Okay. And I'll see, Hope, if we've got questions from any other members.
Doesn't look like we do. So we're really grateful for you joining us this morning,
Hope. Thank you for your oral submission and the written submission as
well. Really appreciate your time, so thank you.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay, members, that was our only
oral submission for this morning, so we just have or whether we wish to private
checks.